Guide to the Beatrice Witkin Papers, 1949 - 1988
Beatrice Witkin Papers, 1949 - 1988
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Witkin, Beatrice.
2006-45
5
8
Beatrice Witkin (1917-1990) was an accomplished composer and one of the first women to produce electronic music compositions.
The materials in the Beatrice Witkin Papers range from her earliest musical compositions to her major works. Notes and secondary literature accompany many of the compositions, and all major works have complete scores.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Given by Steve Witkin of Belgrade, Maine, in July 2006.
Biographical Note
Composer Beatrice Witkin (1917-1990) was born in New York City. She attended Hunter College in New York and did her graduate work at New York University. She studied composition with Mark Brunswick, Roger Sessions, and Stefan Wolpe, and piano with Edward Steuerman. She was also the recipient of the ASCAP Standard Award, and grants from the National Endowment for the Arts, the Ford Foundation, and the Rockefeller Foundation.
Witkin was one of the first women to work in the electronic music idiom. In 1968, she was invited to work at the Electronic Music Studio at the New York University School of the Arts. Two years later, her electronic composition Glissines was a winner in High Fidelity Magazine's Electronic Music Contest.
In 1963, she helped establish the Contemporary Chamber Ensemble, a performing group that commissioned new works. She was a guest composer of the McDowell Colony as well as a longtime member of the Women's Composers Forum and the American Society of Composers, Authors and Publishers.
Chronology of Major Works
Works with an asterisk (*) have corresponding recordings in Scores and Recordings, Wesleyan University.
1960 Duo for Violin and Piano*
1960 Interludes for Solo Flute and Piccolo*
1963 Prose Poem
1964 Contour for Piano*
1964 Parameter for Eight Instruments
1965 Combinations for Thirteen Instruments
1967 Twelve-tone Variations on Quotes by the Beatles for Young People's Orchestra
1968 Fanfare in B and E Flat
1968 Chiaroscuro for Cello and Piano
1968-1969 Triads and Things for Brass Quintet*
1970 Breath and Sounds for Tuba and Stereophonic Tape*
1972-1973 Echologie for Flute and Tape
1977-1978 Report from the Planet Mars
1981 Stephen Foster Revisited Variations for Concert Band
1985 Cantillations of the Bible for String Quartet
Collection Overview
The materials in the Beatrice Witkin Papers range from her earliest musical compositions to her major works. Notes and secondary literature accompany many of the compositions, and all major works have complete scores.
Collection Arrangement
The works follow a chronological order in each box.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Witkin, Beatrice.; Electronic music--Scores.; Electronic music.; Music--United States--20th century.; Composers--United States.; Music--scores.
Detailed Description of the Collection
  - Notebook, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical clippings and concert notes for Jakie Veron Memorial, undated (Folder 2)
  - Notebook with musical composition, undated (Folder 3)
  - Composition, undated (Folder 4)
  - Compositional notes, undated (Folder 5-7)
  - Assorted compositional notes and charts, undated (Folder 8)
  - Nocturne for Solo Cello, Serenade, and Sonata Op. 2, undated (Folder 9)
  - Outline for musical play for children, The Scrolls of David (Folder 10)
  - Composition notebook with college compositions, undated (Folder 11)
  - Music notebook, undated (Folder 12)
    Note: Featuring Poppy Mitrls and Oh let me sleep and so forget the spring, sonnet by Robert Nathan.
  - Music notebooks, undated (Folder 13-16)
  - Music notebook, Wind Band Chart, undated (Folder 17)
  - Jig Jog and Swingaroo, a tone poem in swing, 1938 (Folder 18)
  - Kitchen Music Songs, 1949-1950: photocopies and handwritten (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - I Broke the Plate, 1949
    - If Laughter Were a Broom, 1949
    - Song Discordant, 1949
    - A Needle, a Potato, and a Willow Tree, 1950
  - Does Poppy Live Here?, 1958, 1978
    - Loose scripts, 1958 (Folder 2)
    - Loose scripts and complete script, 1958 (Folder 3)
    - Scripts with cast head shot photos, 1958 (Folder 4)
    - Script with notes on dialogue, 1958 (Folder 5)
    - Clippings about production, 1958 (Folder 6)
    - Scripts, notes, ephemera, and clippings about 1978 production (Folder 7)
  - Unfair to the Bear and Fig for Mother Goose, circa 1957-1958 (Folder 8)
  - Duo for Violin and Piano, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Note: Complete scores.
  - Interludes for Solo Flute and Piccolo, 1960 (Folder 2)
  - The Crisis: a Play, by Gloria Goldsmith with music by Bea Witkin, 1961 (Folder 3)
    Note: Notes, music scores, scripts.
  - Treble Trio, 1962 (Folder 4)
    Note: Music scores.
  - Prose Poem, 1963 (Folder 5-6)
  - Prose Poem, 1963 (Folder 7)
    Note: Text, music notes, concert program.
  - Contour for Piano, 1964 (Folder 8)
  - Parameter for Eight Instruments, 1964 (Folder 9)
    Note: Complete scores and notes.
  - Combinations for Thirteen, 1965 (Box 4)
    - Complete scores (Folder 1)
    - Individual parts (Folder 2-4)
  - Fanfare in B and E flat, 1968 (Folder 5)
    Note: Complete score.
  - Fanfare in B and E flat, 1968 (Folder 6)
    Note: Parts.
  - Triads and Things for Brass Quintet, 1968-1969 (Folder 7)
  - Chiaroscuro for Cello and Piano, 1968 (Folder 8)
  - For Solo Cello, 13 May 1969 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Twelve-tone Variations on Quotes by the Beatles, for Young People's Orchestra, 1967, 1976
    - 2 complete scores. (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Note: One score from 1967 version, one from 1976 revision.
    - Musical notebook and article (Folder 2)
    - Score (Folder 3)
    - Individual parts (Folder 4-7)
  - Electronic music compositions (Folder 8)
    Note: Time Machine (1971), Electronic (1971), Pendulum (no date), Beethoven Piano Sonata (no date), Oboe Trio (no date), and notes.
  - Breath and Sounds for Tuba and Stereophonic Tape, 1970-1972 (Folder 9)
    Note: Complete scores and concert program.
  - Echologie for Flute and Tape, 1972-1973 (Folder 10)
    Note: Complete score, miniature score, and concert program.
  - Report from the Planet Mars, 1977-1978 (Folder 11)
    Note: Four copies.
  - Article clippings used for research for Report from the Planet Mars (Folder 12)
  - Report from the Planet Mars, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 2-8)
    Note: Individual parts.
  - The Iliad of Indian Creek: an Opera Buffa in One Act, music by Beatrice Witkin, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Note: Text, musical notes, and Buffalo Bill Ballad.
  - Stephen Foster Revisited: Variations for Concert Band, 1981
    - Complete score (Folder 2)
    - Condensed score (Folder 3)
    - Instrument parts (Folder 4)
    - Draft scores (Folder 5-6)
    - 2 complete scores and 1 condensed (Folder 7)
    - Draft instrument parts (Folder 8-10)
    - Individual parts (Folder 11)
  - Cantillations for Two Clarinets and Piano, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Note: Program notes.
  - Cantillations: Tropes for Zechariah, 1984 (Folder 2)
    Note: Charts.
  - Cantillations of the Bible for String Quartet, 1985 (Folder 3)
    Note: Lamentations I; Sephardic and Babylonian Lamentations III; V Ashkenazic-Portugese-Bach notes and working charts.
  - Cantillations of the bible for String Quartet, 1985 (Folder 4)
    Note: Individual parts for Lamentations I: I Sephardic and Babylonian.
  - Cantillations Psalm 93, 1986 (Folder 5)
    Note: Notes, program guide, charts.
  - Emerson songs, 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 9-14)